

Teemu Daniel Laajala FICAN Cancer Researcher



b. 1987



Turku, Finland



(+358) 400 842 893



http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7016-7354



teelaa@utu.fi teemu.daniel.laajala@gmail.com

Scientific focus —

- Applied math & machine learning
- Prognostic & predictive modeling
- Preclinical & clinical oncology
- Multi-'omics & translatability
- Open science, data, and source code
- R-programming & CRAN-packages

Other skills -

ΙT

- R, C#, Python, Java, C, Fortran
- · LaTeX, SQL, XML, JSON, Git
- MS Office, Inkscape, GIMP, Adobe suite, HTML/CSS

Languages

· Professional: English & Finnish

· Conversational: Swedish

Linked profiles

- ResearchGate
- Google Scholar
- Stack Overflow
- GitHub
- LinkedIn
- Twitter

Research experience

2018 –	FICAN West (Läntinen Syöpäkeskus, UTU)	Post-doc
2018 –	University of Colorado – Costello Lab (UCDenver)	Post-doc
2013 – 2018	Department of Mathematics & Statistics (UTU) Multiple research topics mainly focused on oncology	PhD student

2013 – 2018 Turku Centre for Biotechnology (UTU, ÅA)

PhD student
PSA-molecule research and models for predicting
progression of prostate and kidney cancer.

with a PhD thesis focus on advanced prostate cancer.

2013 – 2018 Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland (FIMM, HY) Project researcher Head bioinformatician in multiple collaborative projects.

2010 – 2012 Department of Mathematics & Statistics (UTU) Project researcher ChIP-seg method development and analysis of cancer studies.

2008, 2009 Turku Centre for Biotechnology (UTU, ÅA) Summer intern ChIP-seq sequence and diabetes microarray analyses.

Education

2013 – 2018 PhD ('with honours' special mention)

Topic of thesis: Modeling and Prediction
of Advanced Prostate Cancer

University of Turku

2006 – 2012 MSc (Tech) (Bioinformatics, 'exceptional' honors)

Aalto University

Selected publications (First or shared first author)

IF '21-'22	
6.937	Laajala TD*, Murtojärvi M*, et al. <i>ePCR</i> : an R-package for survival and time-to-event prediction in advanced prostate cancer, applied to realworld patient cohorts. Bioinformatics. 2018 Nov 15;34(22):3957-
5.482	3959.
5.462	Huvila J*, Laajala TD*, et al. Combined ASRGL1 and p53 immunohistochemistry as an independent predictor of survival in endometrioid
	endometrial carcinoma. Gynecol Oncol. 2018 Apr;149(1):173-180.
41.316	Guinney J*, Wang T*, Laajala TD*, et al. Prediction of overall survival
	for patients with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer: de-
	velopment of a prognostic model through a crowdsourced challenge
	with open clinical trial data. Lancet Oncol. 2017 Jan;18(1):132-142.
4.379	Laajala TD, et al. Optimized design and analysis of preclinical inter-
1.070	vention studies in vivo. Sci Rep. 2016 Aug 2;6:30723.
12.531	Laajala TD, et al. <i>Improved statistical modeling of tumor growth and</i>
12.331	
	treatment effect in preclinical animal studies with highly heteroge-
	neous responses in vivo. Clin Cancer Res. 2012 Aug 15;18(16):4385-

* = Equal contribution

Researcher

Awards & Funding

Participated in two DREAM challenges resulting in DREAM 9.5 mCRPC Challenge Top Performer (2015) & DREAM Anti-PD1 Response Prediction Challenge Top Performer (2021, ongoing). Rewarded Elias Tillandz -prize 2017 (best scientific publication in Turku BioCity) as first author; again in 2019 as non-first author.

FICAN Cancer Researcher (Finnish Cancer Institute, 2020-2022); NIH grant "Curated prostate cancer data for novel and reproducible prognostic modeling" (2020-2022); Finnish Cultural Foundation (central fund 2014, VS-regional 2018, 2019); DRDP doctoral programme (2014); NIH/NCI DREAM/mCRPC-sponsorship (2016).

Overview

Brief statistics 04/2022: Citation count 1168 & h-index 17 (Google Scholar); ResearchGate score 34.03 (best >10% quantile) & h-index 15; 30+ peer-reviewed articles in PubMed, of which 5+ in >10 IF journals; Stack Overflow best >25% quantile, >3% quantile in R.